<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>opniche</title><link>https://apratap.github.io/blog/</link><description>watever I thought should be public</description><atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="https://apratap.github.io/blog/rss.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2015 23:11:06 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Telemedicine -- On-demand health care becoming reality</title><link>https://apratap.github.io/blog/posts/telemedicine-on-demand-health-care-becoming-reality/</link><dc:creator>Abhishek Pratap (Abhi)</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In US most doctor’s visit last for less than 15-minute provided you are lucky to get an appointment on short notice. The waiting time to see a doctor for the first time can be frustratingly long between 7-21 days. The wait is even longer if you are looking for specialty care[1].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.dropbox.com/s/3rogiu4gi8b6ooc/telemed_post_image1.png?raw=1" width="250" height="100"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think these stats will discourage anyone seeking medical attention for a minor condition to a point where it can't further wait, or an ER visit becomes obligatory.  Needless to say such delays can result in a fat medical bill, longer healing times and further medical complications. However, there is good news. Many of these problems are fixable through technology and are finally attracting entrepreneurs. I am excited to see both established and new players (few examples [3]) creating products for healthcare that are consumer-centric, cost efficient, transparent and time-bound.  Even the big players are adapting.  “We need to flip the system on its head,” said Nancy Gagliano, MD, senior vice president at CVS Health and chief medical officer of CVS/MinuteClinic [2]. I believe the current digital health led disruption of healthcare will fundamentally change the way healthcare is delivered to patients ultimately driving the cost down and at the same time offer higher quality and convenience.  Interestingly enough some of the early health technology products are already proving to be useful. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the eve of Thanksgiving break, I was down with severe throat pain, cold and fever that had lasted five days.I unwillingly picked up the phone to finally see my doctor. Despite being an established patient, I could only be seen the next day. Frustrated and looking for immediate help, I decided to try out a telemedicine company “Dr. On Demand”. Within minutes of app installation, I was in front of a doctor who evaluated my symptoms remotely and prescribed me medications. It took &amp;lt; 1 min of waiting from the comfort of my home and 12 minutes of consultation time and my medications were sent to my local pharmacy (Total Cost: $40, after free first visit without any insurance).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.dropbox.com/s/5obxyxhi8enera4/telemed_post_image2.png?raw=1" width="400" height="300" align="center"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just after my appointment I was able to see the doctor’s notes and follow up advice. Being skeptical, I did visit my primary care doc the next day who made the same diagnosis and wrote the same prescription. It was apparent through a short personalexperience that Telemedicine has arrived. 48% of employers will make Telehealth services available to employees in 2015 [4]. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is important to understand that telemedicine is and will not replace all in-person patient visits, especially where physical examination and/or clinical lab work becomes essential. However, the technology will soon touch many patients seeking medical care directly from the comfort of their home. Under the newly formed Accountable Care Organizations (ACO's) and Patient Centered Medical Home (PCMH), coordinated care remains one of the central goal.  Telemedicine is well positioned to help patients and their care team connect virtually, saving time and overall cost for the healthcare system.  The era of on-demand health concierge companies has finally started taking shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.dropbox.com/s/mm42y482j39h8xv/telemed_post_image3.png?raw=1" width="1300" height="400" align="center"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;
1. http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2014/07/06/sunday-review/waiting-and-waiting.html&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Primary care in the New Health Economy: Time for a makeover (http://pwchealth.com/cgi-local/hregister.cgi/reg/pwc-hri-primary-care-new-economy-2016.pdf)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://apratap.github.io/blog/posts/amia2015-connect-a-thon-bayarea-startups-%2B-medical-informatics-folks/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pati, A “Survey: 48% of employers plan to offer telehealth services by 2015” Mobihealth News September 12, 2014. Accessed October 28, 2015. http://mobihealthnews.com/36545/survey-48-percent-of-employers-plan-to-offer-telehealth-services-by-2015/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>DigitalHealth</category><category>mHealth</category><category>telemedicine</category><guid>https://apratap.github.io/blog/posts/telemedicine-on-demand-health-care-becoming-reality/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2015 22:28:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Medicine -- challenged by technology, its consumer &amp; cost</title><link>https://apratap.github.io/blog/posts/medicine-challenged-by-technology-its-consumer-cost/</link><dc:creator>Abhishek Pratap (Abhi)</dc:creator><description>&lt;div tabindex="-1" id="notebook" class="border-box-sizing"&gt;
    &lt;div class="container" id="notebook-container"&gt;

&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"&gt;
&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Health-care is served from a menu of treatments and guidelines designed decades ago, primarily by the western countries.&lt;/strong&gt;  The dynamics of the world has significantly changed. Approximately 70% of world population is now living in developing countries, and that number is expected to rise to 90% in next 2-3 decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.dropbox.com/s/7h6s25gh6u8t53l/image1.png?raw=1" align="middile" height="450" width="550"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Health care consumers and advocates are now beginning to question the same old ingredients that don't quite serve well the eclectic needs of our growing population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fresh health-care services menu with upfront pricing is needed. One that is cost effective and tailored to their local needs just like our local restaurants. It was refreshing to read in &lt;a href="http://ic2030.org/"&gt;PATH's 2030 report&lt;/a&gt;, how the “jugaad” or frugal innovation is finally catching the attention of westerners innovators.  For mass adoption and any significant impact in the developing world, health-care innovation will need to justify costs at each step of product development.  Innovators now need to bring in affordability for end users at the very center of their product design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also upset to see that the report lacked digital health based innovations. Although, they briefly mention about mobile health based technology and its role in managing chronic diseases, the report did not pick any specific startup disrupting the mHealth sector.  I wanted to read more about those startups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In resource-limited settings where both the number of care providers and costs are limiting factors to provide even basic primary care, digital health can be leveraged to help provide the last mile of care in rural population. Even in developed nations the medical system struggles to produce super health evangelists like Dr. Brenner (from the hotspotter's reading) who care intimately about the well being of a patient just like their mom would.  For example, care in the US is built around single patient-doctor encounters like a primary care visit or an emergency room encounter. However, many of the patients diseases such as diabetes require continual long-term care in close partnership with their care team. Just one-off clinic visits can't capture the longitudinal disease complexities the patient has to live with.  Smart informatics tools could fill this gap by helping the patient capture, understand and manage their disease in close partnership with their doctor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enabling the transformation of doctor driven care to the doctor-patient partnership is a great opportunity for entrepreneurs of this decade. I believe digital health based innovation can help aid in the redesign of health-care services menu for sustainable and tailored care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
</description><category>consumer</category><category>DigitalHealth</category><category>epatient</category><category>medicine</category><guid>https://apratap.github.io/blog/posts/medicine-challenged-by-technology-its-consumer-cost/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2015 21:47:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Digital Health Startups at #AMIA2015</title><link>https://apratap.github.io/blog/posts/amia2015-connect-a-thon-bayarea-startups-%2B-medical-informatics-folks/</link><dc:creator>Abhishek Pratap (Abhi)</dc:creator><description>&lt;div tabindex="-1" id="notebook" class="border-box-sizing"&gt;
    &lt;div class="container" id="notebook-container"&gt;

&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"&gt;
&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="AMIA2015---Connect-a-thon"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amia.org/amia2015/"&gt;AMIA2015&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href="https://www.amia.org/amia2015/connectathon"&gt;Connect-a-thon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="anchor-link" href="https://apratap.github.io/blog/posts/amia2015-connect-a-thon-bayarea-startups-%2B-medical-informatics-folks/#AMIA2015---Connect-a-thon"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amia.org"&gt;AMIA&lt;/a&gt; organized an interesting forum to bring together some of the &lt;em&gt;DigitalHealth&lt;/em&gt; startups in Bay area at their annual &lt;a href="https://www.amia.org/amia2015/"&gt;conference&lt;/a&gt; in San Francisco. The goal was to pair startups with some of the selected AMIA members for a candid mutual learning session/s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally for me it was a great experience to hear from and meet folks form 7 exciting startups in a single room. I would say coming to #AMIA2015 just for this justified my time. The group had engaging converasations and my hope is that some of these discussions would blend into longer term engagements of like minds. Win Win !!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brief notes about each startup present at this meetup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.mangohealth.com"&gt;Mango Health&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;app for medication compliance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;working with PBM - pharmacy benefits managers to offer an enterprise version of the app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.iodine.com/"&gt;Iodine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expert medical info + your reviews of medications. / crowdsource&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;effect of medication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;knowing more about your medication its success, failures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;see which meds are effective for e.g. in depression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hexcare(early startup)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;EHR data integration of the patient generated data  a.k.a data coming self-quantified patients&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;taking data from home&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;chronic illness disease management at home&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;FertilityIQ(early startup)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;information &amp;amp; rating about fertility clinics &amp;amp; doctor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;find clinics with a high rate of success for your fertility needs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://apratap.github.io/blog/posts/amia2015-connect-a-thon-bayarea-startups-%2B-medical-informatics-folks/www.canvasmedical.com"&gt;Canvas Medical&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new interface on top of EMR&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;agile and unstructured data model - ability to customize and adapt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://amino.com/"&gt;Amino&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;design - user experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;connect people to the best care possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;helps consumer finds doctors near them that have experience treating similar patients as you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://ambientclinical.com/"&gt;Ambient Aware&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;spin off from Mayo Clinic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;products&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sepsis sniffer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;emergency dept dashboard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AWARE - manage information in EMR especially for ICU&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
</description><category>AMIA2015</category><category>conferences</category><category>DigitalHealth</category><category>Startups</category><guid>https://apratap.github.io/blog/posts/amia2015-connect-a-thon-bayarea-startups-%2B-medical-informatics-folks/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2015 21:17:07 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>