<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>opniche (telemedicine)</title><link>https://apratap.github.io/blog/</link><description></description><atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="https://apratap.github.io/blog/categories/telemedicine.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2015 23:11:06 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Telemedicine -- On-demand health care becoming reality</title><link>https://apratap.github.io/blog/posts/telemedicine-on-demand-health-care-becoming-reality/</link><dc:creator>Abhishek Pratap (Abhi)</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In US most doctor’s visit last for less than 15-minute provided you are lucky to get an appointment on short notice. The waiting time to see a doctor for the first time can be frustratingly long between 7-21 days. The wait is even longer if you are looking for specialty care[1].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.dropbox.com/s/3rogiu4gi8b6ooc/telemed_post_image1.png?raw=1" width="250" height="100"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think these stats will discourage anyone seeking medical attention for a minor condition to a point where it can't further wait, or an ER visit becomes obligatory.  Needless to say such delays can result in a fat medical bill, longer healing times and further medical complications. However, there is good news. Many of these problems are fixable through technology and are finally attracting entrepreneurs. I am excited to see both established and new players (few examples [3]) creating products for healthcare that are consumer-centric, cost efficient, transparent and time-bound.  Even the big players are adapting.  “We need to flip the system on its head,” said Nancy Gagliano, MD, senior vice president at CVS Health and chief medical officer of CVS/MinuteClinic [2]. I believe the current digital health led disruption of healthcare will fundamentally change the way healthcare is delivered to patients ultimately driving the cost down and at the same time offer higher quality and convenience.  Interestingly enough some of the early health technology products are already proving to be useful. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the eve of Thanksgiving break, I was down with severe throat pain, cold and fever that had lasted five days.I unwillingly picked up the phone to finally see my doctor. Despite being an established patient, I could only be seen the next day. Frustrated and looking for immediate help, I decided to try out a telemedicine company “Dr. On Demand”. Within minutes of app installation, I was in front of a doctor who evaluated my symptoms remotely and prescribed me medications. It took &amp;lt; 1 min of waiting from the comfort of my home and 12 minutes of consultation time and my medications were sent to my local pharmacy (Total Cost: $40, after free first visit without any insurance).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.dropbox.com/s/5obxyxhi8enera4/telemed_post_image2.png?raw=1" width="400" height="300" align="center"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just after my appointment I was able to see the doctor’s notes and follow up advice. Being skeptical, I did visit my primary care doc the next day who made the same diagnosis and wrote the same prescription. It was apparent through a short personalexperience that Telemedicine has arrived. 48% of employers will make Telehealth services available to employees in 2015 [4]. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is important to understand that telemedicine is and will not replace all in-person patient visits, especially where physical examination and/or clinical lab work becomes essential. However, the technology will soon touch many patients seeking medical care directly from the comfort of their home. Under the newly formed Accountable Care Organizations (ACO's) and Patient Centered Medical Home (PCMH), coordinated care remains one of the central goal.  Telemedicine is well positioned to help patients and their care team connect virtually, saving time and overall cost for the healthcare system.  The era of on-demand health concierge companies has finally started taking shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.dropbox.com/s/mm42y482j39h8xv/telemed_post_image3.png?raw=1" width="1300" height="400" align="center"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;
1. http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2014/07/06/sunday-review/waiting-and-waiting.html&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Primary care in the New Health Economy: Time for a makeover (http://pwchealth.com/cgi-local/hregister.cgi/reg/pwc-hri-primary-care-new-economy-2016.pdf)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://apratap.github.io/blog/posts/amia2015-connect-a-thon-bayarea-startups-%2B-medical-informatics-folks/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pati, A “Survey: 48% of employers plan to offer telehealth services by 2015” Mobihealth News September 12, 2014. Accessed October 28, 2015. http://mobihealthnews.com/36545/survey-48-percent-of-employers-plan-to-offer-telehealth-services-by-2015/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>DigitalHealth</category><category>mHealth</category><category>telemedicine</category><guid>https://apratap.github.io/blog/posts/telemedicine-on-demand-health-care-becoming-reality/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2015 22:28:48 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>